Space debris, refuse generated as a result of
space development, is a very serious threat.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
（ナレーション）宇宙開発の
結果として出た廃棄物―
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2076, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
これは 2076年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
しばらく:little while/short while|a while, 目にかかる[めにかかる]:to meet (someone of higher status)|to be recognized (esp. by someone of higher status)/to be visible
（ラジオ）しばらく
お目にかかりませんでしたが―
So I say, "I haven't seen you for
a while, where have you been?"
どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), いでる:to go/to come, ござる:to be
どちらのほうへ
おいででございますかと―
向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 小用[こよう, しょうよう]:trifling matter|urination/urine, 海岸[かいがん]:coast/beach
これに向こうが小用で
海岸のほうにとでも言ったら…
So when he says he was on
a business trip on the beach,
Hoshino
...I say I say to him, "No wonder you look
so tanned, it's because of the sea breeze."
I'm home.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
（ハチマキ）ただいま
（ハルコ）ハチかい？
That you, Hachi?
You're hopeless. Just saying that you'll
be home today doesn't tell me anything.
あんたって子は―
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
“今日 帰る”だけじゃ
分かんないでしょ
何時[いつ]:when/how soon, 何時[なんじ, なんどき]:what time?, 便[びん]:flight (e.g. airline flight)|mail|opportunity, 便[べん]:convenience/service|excreta (esp. faeces), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
何時の便かくらい…
At least tell me when
your flight...
（ハルコ）あら
Oh, my.
Coworkers of mine.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 同僚[どうりょう]:coworker/co-worker/colleague
（ハチマキ）会社の同僚
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
うちが成田(なりた)の
すぐ近くだって言ったら―
When I told them we lived near Narita,
they said they wanted to come visit.
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
遊びに来たいって
Good afternoon.
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
（ユーリ）こんにちは
I hope we're not imposing.
お邪魔[おじゃま]:hindrance/intrusion
（タナベ）お邪魔します
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Geez, I didn't want to take a vacation,
but our ship got destroyed.
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 休暇[きゅうか]:holiday/day off/furlough, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ハチマキ）
…ったく 休暇なんて―
Phase 13
Scenery with a Rocket
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
取りたくなかったん
だけど―
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
俺たちの船が
壊れちまってさ
お前 何かやったのかい？
Did you do something
to it?
（ハチマキ）
俺じゃねえよ
It wasn't me.
Our captain
rammed it into something.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 自ら[おのずから]:naturally/as a matter of course, 自ら[みずから]:oneself|for one's self/personally, 体当たり[たいあたり]:ramming attack/hurling oneself (at)|throwing oneself into (e.g. a role)
船長自ら 体当たりさせて
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, ニュース:news
あっ ひょっとして
この間 ニュースでやってたやつ？
Oh, you don't mean that scare that was
on the news a while ago, do you?
Yes, the Space Defense Front incident.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident
はい 宇宙防衛戦線の事件です
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
船は
なくなってしまいましたが―
We lost our ship, but we managed
to foil the terrorists' plan.
テロリスト:terrorist, 作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations
テロリストの作戦を
防げたんですから
Yuri-san, your Japanese is excellent.
Where did you learn it?
日本語[にほんご, にっぽんご]:Japanese (language)|Japanese as a second language, 上手[じょうず, じょうて]:skill/skillful|flattery, 上手[うわて, かみて]:upper part|upper stream|right side of the stage (audience's or camera's POV)||
ユーリさん 日本語 上手ね
どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount
どちらで勉強されたの？
妻[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 妻[め]:female/woman|wife, 日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people
ああ 妻が日本人でした
My wife was Japanese.
Was?
（ハルコ）でした？
死にました ８年前です
She passed away. It was eight years ago.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハルコ）
あら 悪いこと聞いちゃったわね
Oh, I'm sorry I brought it up.
No, that is all right.
いやあ 大丈夫です
そのことは もう大丈夫
I am okay with it now.
（タナベ）ん？
伏せる[ふせる]:to lie down/to retire/to go to bed (with an illness), 伏せる[ふせる]:to lay something upside down/to turn something over|to cover
はっ…
ユーリさん タナベさん 伏せて
Yuri-san! Tanabe-san! Take cover!
（タナベ）あっ
（ユーリ）えっ？ あっ
（ハチマキ）どうした？
What's wrong?
ぐっ があーっ
危[き]:danger|Chinese "rooftop" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family
（九太郎(きゅうたろう)）危ねえ 危ねえ
よその家じゃなくて よかった
Oh, man, that was close!
I'm glad it didn't hit a neighbor's house!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩 先輩！
Senpai! Senpai!
Say something, Senpai!
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
しっかりしてください 先輩
まっすぐ:straight (ahead)/direct|straightforward, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
（九太郎）
しかし まっすぐ飛ばねえなあ
Damn, this thing totally
refuses to fly straight.
Maybe there's a problem with
the gimbal adjustment, too...
調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
ジンバルの調整も悪かったかなあ
九太郎！
Kyutaro! How many times do I have to tell you
to launch your rockets down at the beach?!
ロケット:rocket, 海岸[かいがん]:coast/beach, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||, なさる:to do, 何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?
ロケットは海岸で飛ばしなさいって
何度 言わせんの！
お客様[おきゃくさま]:guest/visitor|customer
お客様に何かあったら―
If anything happens to our guests, I'm taking
those rockets away, do you hear me?!
母ちゃん[かあちゃん]:mum/mom, ロケット:rocket, 取り上げる[とりあげる]:to pick up|to adopt|to take away|
もう 母ちゃん
そのロケット 取り上げるからね！
What, you don't care
what happens to me?
俺は どうなってもいいのかよ
（九太郎）ん…
I did launch it
out towards the sea.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||
ちゃんと海のほうに飛ばしたさ
But the piece of crap gyro
isn't compatible.
ジャイロ:gyro/gyroscope/gyrocompas, いまいち:one more/another|not quite, 相性[あいしょう]:affinity/compatibility, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
ただ ジャイロと
いまいち相性が悪いんだ
兄貴[あにき, アニキ]:elder brother|one's senior|older man, 挨拶[あいさつ]:greeting|polite set phrase used to express apology, sympathy, congratulations, etc.|speech (congratulatory or appreciative)||
こんにゃろう
１年ぶりの兄貴に これが挨拶か
You little bastard! You haven't seen me
for a year, and this is how you say hello?!
Oh, you're back, bro?
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"
あっ 帰ってたのか 兄ちゃん
ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, でかい:huge/big/gargantuan, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
お前は ずうたいばっかり
でかくなりやがって―
You might have grown some,
but these stunts of yours are still...
昔[むかし]:olden days/former
やるこたあ 昔っから…
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, うたう:to sing|to sing (one's praises in a poem, etc.)/to compose a poem, うたう:to extol/to sing the praises of|to declare
変わんねえな ずうたいも
No, I guess you
haven't grown.
お前 もうすぐ 14だろ？
Aren't you nearly 14?
Screw you! Leave me alone!
放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
（九太郎）
う… うるせーや 放っとけ！
うっ… ああ…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩！
Senpai!
Are you all right?! Senpai!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
大丈夫ですか？ 先輩
I suppose it's
in their blood.
血筋[ちすじ]:lineage/stock/strain, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
（ハルコ）血筋ってやつかしらね
父親[ちちおや]:father, 兄貴[あにき, アニキ]:elder brother|one's senior|older man, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
ほら あの子の父親も兄貴も
宇宙飛行士でしょう？
You see, that boy's father and big brother
are both astronauts.
Huh? Their father is
an astronaut, too?
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（タナベ）えっ お父さんも
宇宙飛行士なんですか？
That's right. He didn't tell you?
（ハルコ）そうよ 聞いてない？
No, ma'am,
not a word.
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
（タナベ）はい 全然
（ハルコ）それとも あれかな？
Or maybe it's that
other thing.
Hachi and Kyuta were the result of us getting
lucky while we were on trips to the moon,
ハチも キュウタも―
夫婦[ふうふ, めおと]:married couple/spouses|his and hers, 旅行[りょこう]:travel/trip, 当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||
夫婦で 月旅行してるときに
当てた子だから―
...so maybe they have
a connection to space.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 縁がある[えんがある]:to be fated to/be linked by fate, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
宇宙に縁があるのかしら
福引き[ふくびき]:lottery/tombola/drawing, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
福引きみたいに言うなよ
Don't make it sound like
a lottery drawing.
How can I put it? It's like Kyutaro
has too much energy pent up inside.
何ていうか―
勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|, 余る[あまる]:to remain/to be left over/to be in excess
勢い余っちゃってるのよね
九太郎は
歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime, 焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered
まだ 13歳なんだから
そんなに焦らなくてもいいのにね
He's still only 13, so I don't see why
he has to be in such a hurry.
Where did Kyutaro-kun go?
九太郎君 どこに行ったんですか？
（ユーリ）へえ
ん？ あっ…
Oh, you are distilling seawater
and then electrolyzing it.
海水[かいすい]:ocean water, 蒸留[じょうりゅう]:distillation, 電気分解[でんきぶんかい]:electrolysis
（ユーリ）海水を蒸留してから
電気分解するんですか
That makes you self-sufficient
as far as fuel is concerned.
燃料[ねんりょう]:fuel, 自給自足[じきゅうじそく]:self-sufficiency
燃料は 自給自足というわけですね
（九太郎）ん…
Yuri Mihairokoh.
兄さん[にいさん, あにさん]:older brother|brother (as older-brother figure in friendly and or work relationship)|(vocative) young man, 同僚[どうりょう]:coworker/co-worker/colleague
ユーリ･ミハイロコフ
星野(ほしの)… 八郎太(はちろうた)兄さんの同僚です
I work with your brother, Hoshino Hachirota.
星野九太郎
Hoshino Kyutaro.
Your hideout is
most impressive.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), アジト:hideout/secret base of operations/safe house
（ユーリ）すごいアジトですね
I rent it from a fisherman that
I know. A thousand yen a year.
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance, 漁師[りょうし]:fisherman, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
（九太郎）
知り合いの漁師さんから借りてんだ
年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 円[えん]:yen/Japanese monetary unit|circle, 円[まる]:circle|entirety|money||
年間 1,000円で
触る[さわる]:to touch/to feel, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
触っちゃ駄目だ！
Don't touch that!
低温[ていおん]:low temperature, やけど:burn/scald
それ低温だから やけどする
It's super-cooled,
so it'll burn you.
Did you make all this
by yourself?
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
これ みんな
自分で作ったんですか？
I swiped 'em from the scrapyard down by
the spaceport. What do you want, anyway?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 港[みなと]:harbour/harbor/port, 港[こう]:harbour, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 廃材[はいざい]:scrap wood/scrap material, 置き場[おきば]:place for something/storehouse, 盗む[ぬすむ]:to steal
宇宙港近くの廃材置き場から
盗んできた
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
何の用？
Oh. I had an idea regarding
your rocket.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, ロケット:rocket
ああ さっきの
ロケットのことなんですけど
I used to ride this when I was in high school.
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（ハチマキ）
高校のときに乗ってたんだ
（タナベ）へえ
It's been sitting around for ages,
so it might not run very well.
ほったらかす:to let aside/to neglect, 吹く[ふく]:to blow (e.g. wind)|to emit|to whistle||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハチマキ）
長いこと ほったらかしてたから
吹けが悪いかもな
You're probably having trouble with low-gravity
disorder and space lag, right?
重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 時差[じさ]:time difference, きつい:intense/severe|determined
低重力障害とか
時差ボケできついんだろ？
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 行ってくる[いってくる]:I'm off/see you later|to go (and then come back)
俺一人で行ってくるから―
I'll go by myself,
so you stay here...
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
お前は家に入ってていいぞ
（タナベ）先輩
- Senpai.
Do you even know
what nampura is?
ナンプラー:nam pla/nam plaa/num pla
ナンプラーって分かります？
野菜[やさい]:vegetable
あ… 野菜？
A vegetable?
やっぱり:too/also|still
ウフッ やっぱり 私も行きます
I think I'd better
go with you.
パソコン:personal computer
九太郎君のパソコンに―
I will copy the navigation and guidance system
that Technora uses onto your PC.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, 誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, システム:system, コピー:copy/photocopy
テクノーラ社が使っている
航行誘導システムをコピーします
This should make
a big difference.
随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible
これで 随分 違うはずですよ
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, コピー:copy/photocopy
そんなの
勝手にコピーしていいの？
Are you allowed to make
copies like that?
It is a crime. But only if someone finds out.
犯罪[はんざい]:crime/offence/offense, バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior)
犯罪です バレればね
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 大根[だいこん, だいこ]:daikon (variety of large white Oriental radish, Raphanus sativus var. longipinnatus)|ham actor, 大根[おおね]:root/source/origin
（ハチマキ）
えーっと あとは大根と
Let's see, all we need
now is a daikon.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩
Senpai, the ones with leaves
taste better. They're sweeter.
葉っぱ[はっぱ, ハッパ]:leaf/blade (of grass)|marijuana, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate, おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive
葉っぱがついてるやつのほうが
甘くて おいしいんですよ
（ハチマキ）へえ
Is that you, Hoshino?
（タクミ）おい 星野か？
（ハチマキ）あ？
Long time, no see!
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
久しぶりだなあ
Takumi, is that you? Geez, you got fat!
太る[ふとる]:to grow fat (stout, plump)/to become fat/to gain weight
お前 タクミか？ 太ったなあ
いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden, そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
いきなり そりゃないだろう
Is that any way to talk
to an old buddy?
This is a friend of mine from high school.
We used to ride our bikes together all the time.
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
高校のときの友達
バイク:motorcycle/motorbike, 乗り回す[のりまわす]:to drive (a car) around/to ride (a bicycle) around
よく２人で バイク乗り回してさ
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
まだ乗ってるか？
You still ride?
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, ワンボックス:minivan/people-mover/6-8 seat automobile with sliding door or doors
いやあ 車を買ったよ
ワンボックス
No, I bought a car. A mini-van.
げっ だっさ
Talk about lame...
う… うるせえな お前だって…
Hey, get off my back! It's not like you...
- Takumi?
しょうゆ:soy sauce/shoyu
（タクミの妻）タッ君
おしょうゆって まだ… あっ
Do we still
have soy sauce...
ああ…
こいつ 星野
This is Hoshino. You know, the old bike buddy
of mine who became an astronaut.
バイク:motorcycle/motorbike, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
ほら バイク友達でさ
宇宙飛行士になったって
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
ああ 宇宙船を買うとか
Oh, the one who was going
to buy a spaceship!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
ああ 宇宙船を買うとか
あっ ああっ よしよし
Sorry, sorry...
What the heck did you
tell her about me?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
お前 どういう説明してんだよ
What's the big deal? It's ancient history now.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
いいだろう？ 昔の話なんだから
Milk? Or pee-pee?
ミルク:milk, おしっこ:wee-wee/pee-pee/number one
ミルク おしっこ？
If she's crying like this,
it must be pee-pee.
泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, おしっこ:wee-wee/pee-pee/number one
この泣き方は おしっこね
Honestly, you'll never be able
to tell the difference.
いつまでたっても
分からないんだから
あ…
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin, 替える[かえる]:to replace|to exchange|to substitute
ちょっと おむつ替えてくるね
I'll go change
her diaper.
（タクミ）ああ
（ハチマキ）タクミ
Sure.
Takumi.
ん？
Congratulations on
getting married, man.
結婚[けっこん]:marriage, おめでとう:congratulations!/an auspicious occasion!, おめでとう:Japanese sweets made with glutinous rice and azuki bean paste
結婚 おめでとう
Thanks. You're getting married,
too, right, Hoshino?
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage
ありがとう
星野もするんだろう？ 結婚
え？
It's hard to believe that
you're settling down.
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
いやあ お前が落ち着くなんてな
You brought your girlfriend home
to meet your parents, right?
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral
彼女 親に紹介しに来たんだろ？
（ハチマキ）な…
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
（タナベ）考えてみたら―
Now that I think about it, me being
introduced to his mother...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral
先輩のお母さんに
紹介されるのって…
シチュエーション:situation
（ハチマキ）
そういうシチュエーション…
I guess it does sort of imply
that kind of situation...
だよな
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（ハチマキ）乗れよ
Get on!
I copy!
コピー:copy/photocopy
ア… アイ コピー
（ハチマキ）何だ？
What's up?
あっ いえ 何でもないです
No, it's nothing.
（ハチマキ）うっ… う…
Damn it, why did Takumi
have to say that?
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ハチマキ）タクミのやつ
余計なこと言いやがって
（タナベ）どうしよう
What am I gonna do? I shouldn't have
said that I'd stay at his house...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 泊まる[とまる]:to stay at (e.g. hotel)|to be docked/to be berthed, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
先輩の家に泊まるなんて
言わなきゃよかった
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 泊まる[とまる]:to stay at (e.g. hotel)|to be docked/to be berthed, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
先輩の家に泊まるなんて
言わなきゃよかった
あっ？
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
うわあ！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, ロケット:rocket, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
先輩 ロケットです こんな近くで
Senpai, it's a rocket! And it's close, too!
Yeah, cool, isn't it?
すっげえ:incredible/unbelievable
ああ すっげえだろ？
実験[じっけん]:experiment, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
どっかの大学の
実験らしいんだけどさ
It's probably some
college experiment.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
すごい すごい
Wow, that's great!
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（ハチマキ）俺も同じこと言ったよ
I said the same thing when I first
saw a launch back in high school!
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
高校のとき 初めて見てな
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||, れっか:deterioration/degradation/drop in quality, れっか:raging fire/conflagration
くそ！ 負けてられっか
Damn it...
I ain't gonna lose
to those guys!
Kyutaro-kun, why do you want
to become an astronaut?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
九太郎君は
どうして宇宙飛行士になりたいの？
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
俺は 宇宙飛行士にはならないよ
I'm not gonna be
an astronaut.
Especially not a half-assed one
like my old man and my brother.
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss, 兄貴[あにき, アニキ]:elder brother|one's senior|older man, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
特に 親父(おやじ)や兄貴みたいな
スチャラカなのには
あ…
エンジニア:engineer
俺は エンジニアになるんだ
I'm gonna be
an engineer.
I'm gonna grow up fast, and go on a day trip
to Mars with a rocket that I built!
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
さっさと大人になって―
エンジン:engine, 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 日帰り旅行[ひがえりりょこう]:day trip
俺のエンジンで
火星 日帰り旅行をやってやる
フッ…
What made you decide to be
an astronaut, Yuri-san?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
ユーリさんは
どうして宇宙飛行士に？
うーん:hmm/well
あっ？ う… うーん…
ん… あっ？
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, バイク:motorcycle/motorbike, ハマる:to fit|to be fit for (a job, etc.)|to fall into||
（ハチマキ）
高校のときはバイクにハマってた
I was hooked on bikes
when I was in high school.
I worked part-time and
saved up the money.
バイト:work (esp. part time or casual), 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, ためる:to straighten/to correct|to falsify, ためる:to save (i.e. in a bank)
バイトして 金 ためてさ
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, いじり:meddling/fumbling/fondling
乗っては いじり
乗っては いじりしてたよ
I'd ride and tinker,
and ride and tinker.
But when I saw a rocket go up from that hill,
I thought, "I'd rather have one of those."
坂[さか]:slope/hill, ロケット:rocket
けどさ
あの坂からロケットを見たとき―
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
あっちがいいなって
思っちまったんだ
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 速い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
大きくて 強くて 速くて
It was big. And powerful. And fast.
Bikes didn't seem to
measure up after that.
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
なんか物足りなくなってさ
And that's why you became
an astronaut?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（タナベ）それで
宇宙飛行士になったんですか？
Yeah.
（ハチマキ）ああ
単純[たんじゅん]:simplicity/simple/uncomplicated
（タナベ）フフッ 単純ですね
That's a simple reason.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハチマキ）悪(わり)いかよ
What's wrong with that?
No, it's your style.
It's just what you'd expect.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（タナベ）いえ 先輩らしいです
とっても:very/awfully|(not) at all
とっても
うっ…
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.)
足 大丈夫か？
Are your feet okay? Between the Earth's gravity
and this sand, I bet they're sore.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 砂浜[すなはま]:sandy beach, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, きつい:intense/severe|determined
地球の重力で しかも砂浜って
結構 きついだろう？
セブン:seven, 遠心[えんしん]:centrifuge, 重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull
（タナベ）大丈夫ですよ
セブンには遠心重力あるし
No, I'm fine. Seven has
centrifugal gravity,
...and I may be your junior up in space,
but we both lived here on Earth.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student
宇宙では後輩だけど―
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time), 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
地球で暮らした時間は
変わらないんですから… うっ
おっと:husband, おっと:uh-oh/oops/sorry
（ハチマキ）おっと
Careful!
無重力[むじゅうりょく]:weightlessness/zero gravity, 勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
無重力と勘違いしたんだろ？
You thought you were
in zero-G, didn't you?
Sorry about that...
すいません
うっ
あっ？
あ…
Three... Two... One...
スリー:three
スリー ツー ワン
イグニッション:ignition
イグニッション
Ignition!
Go, baby, go!
いっけ:a house/a home/a family, いっけ:prefix used to strengthen a derogatory adjective
いっけえーっ！
そうだ そのままー！
That's it! Keep going!
It looks good.
What is your target altitude?
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 高度[こうど]:altitude/height|high-degree
（ユーリ）
いい感じです 目標高度は？
対流圏[たいりゅうけん]:troposphere, 突破[とっぱ]:breaking through/breakthrough/penetration
（九太郎）対流圏突破
Through the troposphere!
対流圏[たいりゅうけん]:troposphere, 突破[とっぱ]:breaking through/breakthrough/penetration
（九太郎）対流圏突破
取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
（ユーリ）あっ 何か取れました
（九太郎）ええっ！？
取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
（ユーリ）あっ 何か取れました
（九太郎）ええっ！？
Something came off.
（九太郎･ユーリ）ああ… あ…
（九太郎）ああっ…
（ユーリ･九太郎）
わあ うわあっ あああっ…
（ハチマキ）あ？
（ハチマキ･タナベ）
うわっ ああっ…
なっ…
Oh, crap! It's gonna rust!
さびる:to rust/to become rusty
（九太郎）くそ！ さびる～
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
くっ… 九太郎 てめえ！
Kyutaro, you bastard!
着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.)
あ～あ
これは もう着られませんね
I suppose I won't be
wearing this again...
あっ…
あ…
Yuri-san! You aren't hurt,
are you?
（九太郎）
ユーリさーん ケガない？
ん？
A compass?
コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.)
コンパス？
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
大事な物？
Was it important?
いえ
No.
Do not worry about it.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
気にしないでください
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
もともと壊れていて
使えなかったんです
It was broken to begin with. It didn't work.
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
（ハチマキ）
おーい ユーリも来てたのか？
Hey! You were out
here, too, Yuri?
Yes, we were launching
rockets together.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, ロケット:rocket, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||
（ユーリ）ええ
一緒にロケットを飛ばしていました
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||
（ハチマキ）ユーリがついてんなら
もっと ちゃんと飛ばしてくれよ
If you're here, Yuri, make sure
those damn things fly right!
That's twice today that I thought I was gonna die.
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
今日だけで
２回 死にそうになってんだ
（ユーリ）ああ すみません
Sorry about that. It looks we didn't reconfigure
the guidance commands sufficiently.
誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, コマンド:(computer) command, 調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination, 不足[ふそく]:insufficiency/shortage/deficiency, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
誘導コマンドが
調整不足だったみたいで
（ラジオ）
いいこと聞いちゃったね ええ？
Wasn't it nice to hear that?
They say you learn a lot from talking
to old people, and that's so true.
年寄り[としより]:old people|trustee of the Japan Sumo Association|senior statesman (of the Tokugawa shogunate)|, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness, 全く[まったく]:really|indeed|good grief (expression of exasperation)
年寄りの話は
無駄がないって 全くだよ
もう ただで…
I mean, you can drink
without paying for it, and...
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
（ハチマキ）はあ…
父ちゃんより食うんじゃねえの？
Is it just me, or does
he eat more than Dad?
合[あい]:between-season wear|together|condition|, 合[ごう]:0.18039 litres (liters)|0.3306 metres square (meters)|one-tenth of the way from the base to the summit of a mountain||, 炊く[たく]:to cook (grains, e.g. rice)|to boil/to simmer
そうなのよ
２人だけのときも４合 炊いてんの
He certainly does. Even when it's just the
two of us, I still cook enough for four.
It makes me feel like my
cooking is appreciated.
作り[つくり]:making|appearance (i.e. attire, make-up)|build (i.e. physique)||, 作り[づくり]:making/forming|form
作りがいがあるわ
飯[めし]:cooked rice|meal|one's livelihood, 飯[まんま, まま]:cooked rice, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 学ラン[がくラン, がくらん]:school uniform for boys, often with stand-up collar, long jacket and loose trousers, 脱げる[ぬげる]:to come off/to slip down/to slip off
おい キュウタ
飯のときぐらい その学ラン 脱げよ
C'mon, Kyuta, at least take off that
school uniform when you're eating.
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 冬休み[ふゆやすみ]:winter vacation, 制服[せいふく]:uniform, 着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.)
大体 冬休みなのに
なんで制服 着てんだ？
Why are you wearing a uniform
during winter vacation, anyway?
It doesn't even fit you,
for crying out loud!
以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|, ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
それ以前に
お前 体に合ってねえや ったく
袖口[そでぐち]:cuff/armhole, 折る[おる]:to break|to fold|to make (origami)|, じゃん:isn't it
袖口 折ってんじゃんかよ
You've got the sleeves
rolled up!
ああ うるせえ！
Get off my case! I'm gonna
make my body fit it!
近々[ちかぢか, きんきん]:soon/nearness/before long, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 制服[せいふく]:uniform, 合わせる[あわせる]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
近々 体を
制服に合わせる予定なんだよ
What are you, a noncommissioned
officer from the history books?
大昔[おおむかし]:great antiquity/old-fashioned/long ago, 下士官[かしかん]:non-commissioned officer
大昔の下士官か お前は
落語[らくご]:rakugo/traditional Japanese comic storytelling/comic story (told by a professional storyteller)
ねえ ユーリさんって 落語 聞く？
Say, Yuri-san, do you
listen to Rakugo?
落語[らくご]:rakugo/traditional Japanese comic storytelling/comic story (told by a professional storyteller)
（ユーリ）落語ですか？
Rakugo?
（ハルコ）そう
Right. Japanese traditional
comical speech.
ジャパニーズ:Japanese (people, language), トラディショナル:traditional, コミカル:comical, スピーチ:speech
ジャパニーズ トラディショナル
コミカルスピーチ
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
（ユーリ）面白そうですね
It sounds very interesting.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
（ハルコ）
よかったら 一緒に行く？
Would you care to go see a show with me?
- It was broken to begin with. It didn't work.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
（ハルコ）
よかったら 一緒に行く？
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
（ユーリ）もともと壊れていて
使えなかったんです
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
（ユーリ）もともと壊れていて
使えなかったんです
You'd never guess it, but I'm a huge fan.
Why would he carry something
around if it was broken?
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 持ち歩く[もちあるく]:to carry around/to carry on one's person
（九太郎）
なんでそんな物 持ち歩いてんだろ
フィー:phi
（ハチマキ）
はい 星野 何だ フィーか
Hoshino residence. Oh, it's just you, Fee.
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
（フィー）なんだとは失礼ね
Gee, it's nice to see you, too.
Hachi, what happened to your nose?
鼻[はな]:nose
ハチ あんた 鼻 どうしたの？
ロケット:rocket
ロケットにやられた
It got hit by a rocket.
（フィー）はあ？
（ハチマキ）
んなことはいいよ 何？
Don't worry about it. So, what's up?
I have great news.
We got ourselves a new spaceship.
ニュース:news
（フィー）いいニュースよ
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes), 新造[しんぞう, しんぞ]:new|unmarried woman of about 20|newly-married woman|, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
私たちの新しい宇宙船が決まったの
ピッカピカの新造船だよ
A new one, fresh out
of the wrapper!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
（ハチマキ）ほんとか！？
Seriously?!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
ほんとよ ほんと
Cross my heart.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, ヒロイン:heroine
まあ
宇宙を救ったヒロインだからね
Well, I am the heroine
who saved space, after all.
褒美[ほうび]:reward/prize
ご褒美ってことでしょ
It's probably my
reward for that.
よく言うぜ
Get over yourself.
映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, スペック:specification, データ:data/datum, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
映像やら スペックやらのデータを
送っておくから 見といて
I'm sending you some images
and the specs, so look 'em over.
来週[らいしゅう]:next week, 操船[そうせん]:handling a ship, シミュレーション:simulation
来週から
操船シミュレーションやるから―
We're starting ship-handling simulations
next week, so tell the others.
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
２人にも伝えて いるんでしょ？
They're with you, right?
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
（ハチマキ）ああ 伝えとくよ
Yeah. I'll pass it along.
Need to ask
you something.
Well, I'll leave you
to it, then.
Need to ask
you something.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（フィー）じゃ 頼んだわよ
Need to ask
you something.
Sure. Give my best
to your husband and Al.
旦那[だんな]:master (of a house, shop, etc.)|husband (informal)|sir||, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（ハチマキ）
ああ 旦那さんとアルに よろしく
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
そんじゃ また宇宙で
See you up in space.
Kyutaro, that compass...
コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.)
（ハチマキ）
九太郎 お前 そのコンパスは―
奥さん[おくさん]:wife/your wife/his wife, 形見[かたみ]:memento/keepsake/souvenir
ユーリの奥さんの形見だ
It belonged to
his late wife.
ああっ…
奥さん[おくさん]:wife/your wife/his wife, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
（ハチマキ）
ユーリの奥さんは宇宙で死んだんだ
Yuri's wife died
in space.
Yuri became a debris hauler
so he could find that compass,
壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.), コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.)
お前の壊したコンパスは―
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
ユーリが
わざわざ デブリ屋になって―
...which he finally did after six years,
and you just destroyed it.
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
６年かけて 見つけた物なんだよ
行ってこい 今すぐ
Get out there. Right now.
He said he was going
to the beach.
海岸[かいがん]:coast/beach
海岸に行くって言ってた
Apologizing won't fix that compass,
but get out there and apologize, anyway.
謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise
謝っても どうにもならねえが
謝ってこい！
（九太郎）ああっ…
ロケット:rocket, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ハチマキ）
それに お前 もうロケット やめろ
And give up on those
rockets of yours.
迷惑[めいわく, べいこく]:trouble/bother/annoyance, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
人に迷惑がかかる
They cause nothing
but trouble.
Space isn't the fun, happy place you think it is.
People sometimes die up there.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate
宇宙は お前が考えてるほど
甘かねえんだ！
人間が死ぬことだってある
It's not a game for
irresponsible little kids!
責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||, 遊び[あそび]:playing|play (margin between on and off, gap before pressing button or lever has an effect)
責任 取れないガキの遊びとは
違うんだよ！
（九太郎）んん… うるせえ！
Screw you!
（タナベ）あっ？
Oops, there they go.
始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
（ハルコ）おおっ 始まった
（タナベ）ええっ？
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
てめえ やりやがったな
Okay, now you've
pissed me off!
口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, 遊び[あそび]:playing|play (margin between on and off, gap before pressing button or lever has an effect), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
口先だけの宇宙飛行士に
遊びなんて言わせねえぞ！
No astronaut who's all talk
is gonna call my rockets a game!
ガキが！
You runt! Don't get so cocky over launching
a rocket that doesn't even fly straight!
まっすぐ:straight (ahead)/direct|straightforward, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump, ロケット:rocket, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
まっすぐ飛ばないロケット
上げたぐらいで いい気になんな
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, まっすぐ:straight (ahead)/direct|straightforward, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
てめえこそ
まっすぐ目標に向かえよな
Look who's talking! You're not exactly
heading straight for your target, either!
When are you finally get
that spaceship of yours?!
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
いつんなったら
宇宙船 手に入れんだよ
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 事情[じじょう]:circumstances/consideration/conditions
ガ… ガキには分からねえ
大人の事情があんだよ
You've got other responsibilities when you're
an adult! A runt like you wouldn't understand!
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 事情[じじょう]:circumstances/consideration/conditions, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
何が大人の事情だ
怖がって待ってるだけだろうが
Adult responsibilities, my ass!
You're just
waiting because you're scared!
What do you mean,
waiting?!
待ってるって？
中途半端[ちゅうとはんぱ]:halfway/half measures/unfinished, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, 適当[てきとう]:suitable/proper|noncommittal, 落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||
中途半端にカッコつけて
適当なところに落ち着いて
Sure, you talk the talk, but you settled down
and got complacent the first chance you got!
（ハチマキ）
何言ってんだ このガキ！
What would you know
about it, runt?!
ガキって言うな！
Don't call me a runt! The only thing you
ever beat me at was being born before me!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 取り柄[とりえ]:worth/redeeming feature/merit
早く生まれたこと以外
取り柄 ねえくせに！
へっ
Aw, that's so cute!
People can talk all they want about
possibilities and dreams when they're kids!
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
止めなくていいんですか？
Shouldn't we stop them?
It'll be fine.
取り柄[とりえ]:worth/redeeming feature/merit
大丈夫 うちの男どもは
殺しても死なないのが取り柄だから
Don't talk so big,
you space garbage man!
The good thing about the men in this family
is that they don't die easily.
Now you're making fun of my job, huh?! Step outside!
はあ？
But you know what? That's a very important thing.
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
でもね
それはとても大事なことなのよ
- Bring it on! I'll kick your ass!
Oh...
はあ…
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（ハルコ）タナベさん
いい宇宙飛行士ってのはね
Tanabe-san, you can always
spot a good astronaut.
They're the ones who come
home safe, no matter what.
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 帰ってくる[かえってくる]:to return/to come back
必ず生きて帰ってくる人よ
あ…
（九太郎）ナメんな
Don't screw with me!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
てめえみてえな
スチャラカ宇宙飛行士に―
No way is a... half-assed astronaut
like you... gonna beat me!
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||
負けるかってんだ！
手ごわい[てごわい]:difficult/tough/formidable
（九太郎）手ごわくなったでしょ？
He's gotten stronger,
hasn't he?
Crap... I let
my guard down.
くっそう:crouched burial, 油断[ゆだん]:negligence/carelessness/inattention
（ハチマキ）くっそう 油断した
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きで ガキやってんじゃねえや！
I'm not a kid because I wanna be one!
Yuri-san!
ユーリさーん
（ユーリ）あっ…
Oh, my. What is the matter?
Are you planning a nighttime launch?
夜間[やかん]:at night/nighttime, 打ち上げ[うちあげ]:launching|end (of a theatrical run, etc.)|closing party (e.g. a theater show)
あれ？ どうしたの？
夜間打ち上げ？
コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.)
その… あの… コンパス
Um... About your compass...
（ユーリ）うん…
Just now, I was reminiscing
about something.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
今 ちょっと
思い出してたんですけど―
Back when I was 20 or so, I had many things on
my mind, and I wandered all over the Earth.
二十歳[はたち]:20 years old|twenty, 二十歳[はたとせ]:twenty years, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
私は 二十歳(はたち)くらいのころ
思うところがあって―
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, ブラブラ:dangling heavily/swaying to and fro/swinging, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
地球中を
ブラブラしていたことがあるんです
あっ？
I did not know where to direct my energy.
It was because I was young.
エネルギー:energy, 使い道[つかいみち]:purpose/utility|way to use something
エネルギーの使い道が
分からなかったんですね
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number)
若かったから
It was not only that. There were many other
things that I did not understand.
それだけじゃない
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
分からないことは
他にもたくさんありました
何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
自分は何者なんだろう
What is the "self"? What is the "other"?
他者[たしゃ]:another person/others
他者とは何だろう
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
何がいいことで
何が悪いことなんだろう
What does "good" mean? What does "evil" mean?
What is space? What is the Earth?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe
宇宙って何だろう
地球って何だろう
うろこ:scale (of fish, snake, etc.)|serif (on kana or kanji (e.g. in Mincho font)), 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 瞬間[しゅんかん]:moment/second/instant, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, ながら:while/during|while
目からうろこの落ちる瞬間が
来るのを期待しながら―
I walked and walked, hoping
that there would be an instant...
...when the scales would
fall from my eyes.
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 歩く[あるく]:to walk
結構 歩きました
Having something that is beyond doubt
is a wonderful thing, is it not?
疑い[うたがい]:doubt/question/uncertainty, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
疑いようのないものを
持ってるのって―
すばらしい:wonderful/splendid/magnificent
すばらしいことだと思いませんか？
フッ…
疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 確証[かくしょう]:positive proof, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform
私は 疑問ばかり持ってたから
それを確証に変えたかったんです
I had nothing but questions, so I wanted
to turn them into certainty.
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
そんな感じで
ブラついていたら―
And so, wandering around
like that,
...I came across an old man in North America
who used to be a sailor.
北米[ほくべい]:North America, 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 船乗り[ふなのり]:getting on board|sailor/seaman, 老人[ろうじん]:the aged/old person, 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
北米で
元船乗りの老人に出会ったんです
The stars were bright
and clear that night.
星[ほし]:star|offender|star point (in go)||, 星[せい]:Chinese "star" constellation (one of the 28 mansions)|Singapore
星がよく出てました
The old man laughed
at my questions.
疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt, 老人[ろうじん]:the aged/old person, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
私の疑問は
老人に笑われてしまいました
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number), 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
“お若い方―”
He said, "Young man, you try too hard to put
everything into clear-cut categories."
物事[ものごと]:things/everything, はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
“あなたは物事を 何でも
はっきりさせようとしすぎる”って
ああ… うん 九太郎君
Kyutaro-kun, where do you think the boundary
is between the Earth and space?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 境目[さかいめ]:borderline/boundary, 辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc.
宇宙と地球の境目って
どの辺だと思う？
上空[じょうくう]:sky/the skies/high-altitude sky, 熱圏[ねつけん]:thermosphere, キロメートル:kilometer/kilometre, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
ああ… それは 上空熱圏
100キロメートルくらいから―
Well, there's a sharp drop in atmospheric density
up past 100km in the upper thermosphere.
急激[きゅうげき]:sudden/precipitous/radical, 大気[たいき]:atmosphere, 密度[みつど]:density, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate, キロメートル:kilometer/kilometre, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
急激に大気密度が減って
200キロメートルくらいからが…
Then at 200km,
there's...
うーん:hmm/well
（ユーリ）うーん…
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression, 境目[さかいめ]:borderline/boundary
私の感じでは
ないんですよね 境目が
The way I see it, there isn't one.
There is no boundary.
No. There are no boundaries
in the world.
うん ないんだ
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 境目[さかいめ]:borderline/boundary, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
世界に境目なんて
なんか それでいいと思いますよ
I think that is how
it should be.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 形見[かたみ]:memento/keepsake/souvenir, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
フッ… 実を言うとね
この形見を見つけたら―
To tell you the truth, I had planned to quit being
a debris hauler once I found this compass.
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
デブリ屋を
辞めようと思っていたんです
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 居る[いる]:to be (of animate objects)|to stay|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing, to have been ..ing), 居る[おる]:to be (animate)|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing)|indicates contempt or disdain for another's actions, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
これを見つけ出すこと以外で
宇宙に居続ける理由がなかったから
Because aside from finding this,
I had no reason to stay in space.
But perhaps what that
old man said is correct.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 老人[ろうじん]:the aged/old person, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
でも やっぱり あの老人の
言うとおりかもしれません
ん？
Space... The Earth... Guideposts...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 道しるべ[みちしるべ]:guidepost|guide|tiger beetle (esp. the Japanese tiger beetle, Cicindela japonica)
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
Senpai! Too far!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 道しるべ[みちしるべ]:guidepost|guide|tiger beetle (esp. the Japanese tiger beetle, Cicindela japonica)
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 行き過ぎ[いきすぎ, ゆきすぎ]:going too far/going to extremes
（タナベ）先輩 行き過ぎ
（ハチマキ）ああっ？
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 道しるべ[みちしるべ]:guidepost|guide|tiger beetle (esp. the Japanese tiger beetle, Cicindela japonica)
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 道しるべ[みちしるべ]:guidepost|guide|tiger beetle (esp. the Japanese tiger beetle, Cicindela japonica)
宇宙とか 地球とか
道しるべとか―
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
ほら あそこ
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ
Look over there!
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
ほら あそこ
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
ほら あそこ
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
あまり関係ないみたいです
Those things don't seem all that important.
And so... Thank you for
breaking my compass.
コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.), 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.), ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
だから コンパス壊してくれて
ありがとうね
（九太郎）ああ…
うーん:hmm/well
うーん… よく分かんね
I don't really
understand.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|
実は 私にも
よく分かってないんです
To tell you the truth, I don't really get it either.
アハハハ…
（タナベ）ユーリさーん
Yuri-san!
（ハチマキ）
何やってんだ？ そんなとこで
What're you doing
out here?
（ユーリ）ああ すいません
Sorry.
Come, let's go back. It is quite cold here.
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
もう 帰りましょう
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 寒い[さむい, さぶい]:cold (e.g. weather)|uninteresting (esp. joke)/lame
さすがに寒い あっ…
Kyutaro-kun, would you mind
doing something for me?
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
九太郎君
ちょっと お願いしていいかな？
♪～
Here.
（ハチマキ）ほれ
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
あっ ありがとうございます
Thanks.
Sorry I'm late.
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
（ユーリ）遅くなっちゃって
（ハチマキ）ん？
Damn it, Kyutaro's rocket bug
has gotten even worse...
ロケット:rocket, 病[やまい]:illness/disease|bad habit, 病[いたずき, いたつき]:pain/trouble|illness, 悪化[あっか]:(suffer) deterioration/growing worse/aggravation, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
九太郎のやつ
ロケット病が悪化しやがってよ
食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat, いじる:to touch/to tamper with|to grope about
食事中もいじってんだぜ
He was even fiddling around
with it at the dinner table!
へえ
We have completed
our takeoff sequence.
離陸[りりく]:takeoff, シークエンス:sequence, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination, いたす:to do
（アナウンス）離陸シークエンスを
終了いたしました
We are now beginning our atmospheric
flight sequence,
当[とう]:this (business organisation or place), 当[はた]:or|furthermore|perhaps||, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 赤道[せきどう]:equator, 圏内[けんない]:(being) within range (radio, commuting, etc.)/(being) within the sphere (e.g. of influence), 飛行[ひこう]:aviation/flight|to fly, 飛行[ひぎょう]:flying without hindrance, シークエンス:sequence
当機はこれより 赤道までの
圏内飛行シークエンスに…
...which will last until
we reach the equator.
It should be any time now.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon
さて そろそろか
Also, we ask that all passengers
remain in their seats...
For what? See something?
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
何が？ 何か見えんの？
辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|
あっ うちの辺り？
...until the flight crew says that it
is safe to move about the cabin.
Isn't that near my house?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
えっ 先輩の家(うち)が見えるんですか？
What, can we see your
house from here?
やった！
（ハチマキ）ああっ！？
He did it!
Oh, man, that little maniac
did it...
ありゃあ:oh/ah/I'll be darned, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
ありゃあ
やりやがった あいつ
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
すごいじゃないですか 九太郎君
Kyutaro-kun is pretty amazing,
isn't he?
If he keeps this up, people are
gonna think he's a terrorist...
間違う[まちがう]:to make a mistake/to be incorrect/to be mistaken
こんなことして
テロと間違われるぞ
あれのフェアリングにな
Want to know what's
in its nose cone?
（ハチマキ･タナベ）えっ？
コンパス:pair of compasses/compass (for drawing circles, etc.)
俺のコンパスが入ってるんだ
My compass
is in there.
（タナベ）あ…
Yuri? You're...
ユーリ お前…
You seem different.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
なんか変わった？
フッ…
No big deal. I'll catch up
with him soon enough.
なあに:what|what?, 追いつく[おいつく]:to catch up (with)/to draw level|to be compensated
（九太郎）
なあに すぐに追いつくさ
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Turning Point
Next Time
It's an order from the
assistant manager.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
（エーデル）
係長補佐命令
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
（ラビィ）
社内恋愛を禁止する！
Office romances
are prohibited!
（リュシー）えっ！
狭い[せまい]:narrow/confined/small, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
フンッ 心の狭い親父だな
This is one
narrow-minded dad.
（リュシー）
チェンシンさん
Cheng-Shin-san?
（ハチマキ）するか？
Do you want to do it?
はい！
Excuse me?!
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
寝たの？
（ラビィ）はい！
Have you slept with him?
Excuse me?!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（ハチマキ）
ちゃんと最後まで…
All the way...
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
はい！
（フィー）うるさい！
Excuse me?!
Shut up!
（課長）
ああっ… 何か言った？
Did you say something?
嫌み[いやみ]:disagreeableness/disagreeability/gaudiness
（ハチマキ）
嫌み言うなよ
Don't get so
sarcastic on me!
性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
性格ブスですから
I can't help it. I'm ugly
on the inside, after all.
かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
うん かわいそうだよねえ
Right, I feel sorry
for them.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
課長補佐命令
It's an order from the assistant
section chief.